<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>homepage title on Eduardo&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://ebellani.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in homepage title on Eduardo&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ebellani.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>CQRS as nominalism</title>
      <link>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/cqrs-nominalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/cqrs-nominalism/</guid>
      <description>A theme that I think is important to understand a lot of modernity and the IT sector in particular, is nominalism.1
So, what is Nominalism, and why does it matter? I&amp;rsquo;ll start with a concrete case and work my way to the abstract definition. The case in point is a somewhat popular architecture tactic, CQRS.
What is CQRS? Here is an authoritative word on it(Young 2010):
 Command and Query Responsibility Segregation (CQRS) originated with Bertrand Meyer’s Command and Query Separation Principle</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to stand out in your career, the shortest version I know</title>
      <link>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/stand-out-short/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/stand-out-short/</guid>
      <description>Someone asked me about this, so I feel it might help people out there.
The short, no nonsense advise I give to people on standing out as a programmer:
 Generate results Make your boss look good Join a relevant open source project  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recruitment and Selection of high performing programmers</title>
      <link>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/rec-sel-programmers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/rec-sel-programmers/</guid>
      <description>What could be more important for a technology company than great software? High performing software developers and their teams. After all, they are the ones who actually create and maintain that great software.
But do they really make a difference? I&amp;rsquo;ll let the numbers speak for themselves. Here are the typical variations in:(Steve 2014)
 Individual performance 20 to 1, Team performance 10 to 1, Method performance 1.2 to 1.  One can find a compelling illustration of these data on (Oram and Wilson 2010).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a good manager?</title>
      <link>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/what-is-a-good-manager/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/what-is-a-good-manager/</guid>
      <description>It is hard to do science without proper definitions. So what is a manager?
Abstracting from (Horstman 2016), my definition of a manager is the following:
 A manager continuously balances present output with creating the conditions of future output.
  Figure 1: The Good Sheperd, emblem found in a Roman catacomb, sec III
  As one can see, this definition is similar to an investor. That is expected, since a manager is an investor of a company&amp;rsquo;s resources.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is chatGPT replacing you? or: The nature of the intellectual act</title>
      <link>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/ai-intellectual-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/ai-intellectual-act/</guid>
      <description>I have come across people claiming to fear being replaced by bots, specially chatGPT and other large language models (LLM). In this article I&amp;rsquo;ll take such statements at face value, despite my reservations about the sincerity of many of them.
The short answer is to the question in the title is no, you will not get replaced. The longer answer is below.
 Figure 1: Rudolph, Conrad. The Mystic Ark: Hugh of Saint Victor, Art, and Thought in the Twelfth Century.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An illustrated way to enable openVPN on Qubes OS 4.1.2</title>
      <link>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/vpn-qubes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/vpn-qubes/</guid>
      <description>In my view, Qubes OS lives up to its motto: A reasonably secure operating system. I use it for work and personal matters every day.
One challenging bit, when you use it in a work setting specially, is to set up a VPN qube for your app qubes.
There are probably other ways to do this, but the way I chose to structure my setup was the following:
 After you create your app qube for the VPN and assuming your template is Debian, go to the template terminal (Debian 11) and run:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
