<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>blog on Eduardo&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://ebellani.github.io/categories/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in blog on Eduardo&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ebellani.github.io/categories/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>blog section title</title>
      <link>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a good manager?</title>
      <link>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/what-is-a-good-manager/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/what-is-a-good-manager/</guid>
      <description>It is hard to do science without proper definitions. So what is a manager?
Abstracting from (Horstman 2016), my definition of a manager is the following:
A manager balances present output with creating the conditions of future output.
 Figure 1: The Good Sheperd, emblem found in a Roman catacomb, sec III
  As one can see, this definition is the same as the one for an investor. That is correct.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is chatGPT replacing you? or: The nature of the intellectual act</title>
      <link>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/ai-intellectual-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/ai-intellectual-act/</guid>
      <description>I have come across people claiming to fear being replaced by bots, specially chatGPT and other large language models (LLM). In this article I&amp;rsquo;ll take such statements at face value, despite my reservations about the sincerity of many of them.
The short answer is to the question in the title is no, you will not get replaced. The longer answer is below.
 Figure 1: Rudolph, Conrad. The Mystic Ark: Hugh of Saint Victor, Art, and Thought in the Twelfth Century.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An illustrated way to enable openVPN on Qubes OS 4.1.2</title>
      <link>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/vpn-qubes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ebellani.github.io/blog/2023/vpn-qubes/</guid>
      <description>In my view, Qubes OS lives up to its motto: A reasonably secure operating system. I use it for work and personal matters every day.
One challenging bit, when you use it in a work setting specially, is to set up a VPN qube for your app qubes.
There are probably other ways to do this, but the way I chose to structure my setup was the following:
 After you create your app qube for the VPN and assuming your template is Debian, go to the template terminal (Debian 11) and run:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
